(upbeat music)
- [Instructor] The next
concept that is very important
is that of marginal rate of substitution.
The concept of marginal
rate of substitution
is very important and it is based
on what we have already learned before
in terms of marginal utility.
And so let's first say what
conceptually MRS means.
MRS is the slope of one
indifference curve, okay?
It's a slope of the indifference curve
at a certain combination of x1 and x2.
Let me say it again.
So suppose you have certain combination
of good one and good two, x1, x2
and you know that through
that particular bundle,
there is an indifference
curve going through.
The relative preference between good one
and good two is given, to a large extent,
by how steep is that indifference curve?
If it's very steep, it means
that this person values good
one a lot relative to good two.
And if it's very flat,
means that this consumer
values good two highly relative
to good one.
So MRS contains, in that sense,
a lot of information but
mathematically, but okay,
so we know that contains
a lot of information
but we just need to know
what is the easiest way,
what is the correct way
to find it mathematically
every time we have a
specific utility function.
And that is what this slide is about.
The MRS, also known as the
marginal rate of substitution.
And we are learning that is the slope
of an indifference curve.
And this is why it's dx2/dx1
in this highlighted equation
is gonna be given by the ratio
of MU1 and MU2 with a
minus sign before that.
So how do we know this last equality
that the MRS equals
minus MU1 divided by MU2?
Well, this is what we're gonna prove here.
We know first that an
indifference curve is such
that the satisfaction
level is constant at some,
let's say k value.
We can use something that you've learned
in your calculus classes core
as the total differentiation
and total differentiation
is taking this equation
and taking the total
differentiation of it.
And that total differentiation
of it is written like this.
First is the change of x1
multiply by how sensitive
U is with respect to x1,
which is given by the
partial derivative of U
with respect to x1 plus how
sensitive is D2 function
with respect to the second good
times how big the change
of that good two is,
which is represented here again by dx2.
And that should be equal
to the total change
in the utility that we will call here dk.
However, dk must be zero
because k is constant.
So dk cannot be different
than zero, it must be zero.
That is that we can use this knowledge,
we can use this knowledge or
this fact into this equation
but that's not the only thing we can use.
We also need to notice that
the partial with respect
to x1 and x2 are simply
the marginal utilities.
So we can rewrite this
guy like this using dk0
and using that the derivatives
of U with respect to x1
and x2 simply are MU1
and MU2 respectively.
So we have this equation.
From this equation, we can
form or solve for dx2, dx1
which is the slope of
the indifference curve.
To do that, we need to
divide both sides by dx1.
And after we have done that,
we can solve indeed for dx2/dx1.
If we do that, we will get this equation,
which is exactly what we wanted to show.
Let's just for the sake of comprehension
do that on the iPad as well.
Marginal rate of substitution.
Okay?
Let's put it in a nicer place.
Okay, cool.
So we will try to prove that the slope
of a indifference curve
is the same as minus MU1 divided by MU2.
This is what we want to prove.
And to do that, we will
start again by saying, okay,
along one indifference curve,
the utility level is fixed at a level k.
Second, we will say,
we can take total differentiation of this
and this is going to be the impact of x1
on U times the change
of x1 plus the impact
of x2 on utility times the change in x2.
And they will be equal
to the change in utility.
However, as we have seen before, oops.
However, as we have seen before,
this guy here must be zero.
And these guys here are
MU1 and MU2 respectively.
And therefore, we can
rewrite this equation
as MU1 dx1 plus MU2 times dx2 equals zero.
So from this point, we can
do, we can divide both sides
by the dx1 and we will have this.
From this point, we can subtract MU1
from both sides and we
will have the following.
Well, we can subtract MU1 from both sides
and also divide both sides by MU2.
And we will get this.
And this is exactly what we wanted.
So we have been able to
show what we're looking for.
Okay, let us now do some
examples of calculating MRS.
Let's say we're going to do,
we will do similar functions
that we have just before.
So let's start with some Cobb-Douglas.
Suppose the utility function
is x1 squared times x2.
So MRS, remember is, oops.
MRS, okay, is minus MU1 divided by MU2.
And MU1 is the partial
of U with respect to x1
and MU2 is the partial
of x, sorry, partial of U
with respect to x2.
So with that in mind, we can
calculate the partial of X
of U with respect to
x1, which would be two
x1 times x2.
And the partial of U with respect to x2
or MU2 would be x1 squared times one.
So we get this, we can
simplify a little bit
and we will get two
times x2 divided by x1.
So that would be our MRS
for the first function.
Let's do another example.
Example two, finding MRS.
This time for the utility function equals.
Oops, sorry about that.
Utility function equals
x1 times x2 square root.
Okay?
So in this case, we will say that again,
MRS equals
minus MU1 divided by MU2.
Let's not write the whole
partial derivative this time
because it's not necessary.
We know that MU1 is a partial
of U with respect to x1.
So in this case, we can
directly write x2 square root
because that is the partial
of x of U with respect to x1
and the minus sign here is simply the one
that is coming from there.
Okay?
And with that in mind,
we can now calculate the partial
of U with respect to x2, which would be x1
times 1/2 x2 minus 1/2.
So it's interesting, but now
this can be also simplified.
The way we simplify this is by noting
that having 1/2 in the
denominator is the same
as having two in the numerator.
That's the first thing.
The second thing is that we have x2 power
to something both in the
denominator and the numerator
and we can bring those
together to the numerator.
So it would be x to power to 1/2 plus 1/2
and that plus 1/2 will come from this.
It would be x to 1/2 from
what we already knew.
It's in the numerator minus
because there is also something
in the denominator,
1/2 because 1/2, sorry,
minus minus 1/2 because
minus 1/2 is the exponent
in the denominator for x2.
And we know that in the
denominator, we also have x1.
So all in all, this will
simplify to two times, sorry,
minus two times x2 divided by x1.
You might be thinking, wait a second,
where have we seen this before?
And the answer would be
in the previous example.
How come these two utility functions,
this guy here, this guy here
and this guy here
have the same MRS?
Well, it is because these
two functions actually
are representing the same preferences.
They can be written
as an increasing
transformation of the other.
And as we had anticipated before,
if they represent the same preferences,
they will have the same indifference maps,
they will have the same slopes
for the indifference curves,
meaning they will have the same MRS.
So all these coincidence is
actually not a coincidence,
it's a mathematical
implication of the definitions
and the math concepts that are applied
to indifference curves,
uniqueness of utility functions and MRS.
Finally, we will do an
example of a function
that is of perfect substitutes.
So we're gonna do it here.
Example three, we're
going to do utility, x1
plus let's say five times x2.
So for utility x1 plus five times x2,
we can calculate again also the MRS.
And the MRS would be, as
always, MU1 minus ahead of that
or minus MU1 divided by MU2.
MU1, in this perfect complements
preference, is very simple.
It's simply one.
So it would be minus one in the numerator
and the MU2 would be simply five.
So in this case,
we will simply have
that the MRS is minus 1/5.
This is an important result
because it's actually generalizable
for perfect complements.
Okay, so we're gonna
write here, MRS for...
Actually, we're gonna write it with white
so we keep our convention
of having white for notes
and yellow for examples.
So the MRS
for perfect substitutes
is always
constant.
Why is that?
This is actually part of the definition
or this is another way to
define perfect substitutes.
Perfect substitutes have the same rate
of substitution regardless
of the combination
or regardless of the
bundle we are considering.
So by definition, the perfect
substitutes preferences
will have a constant MRS.
If you remember, the indifference curves
for perfect substitutes preferences
were having indifference curves
that would look like this.
They were all parallel lines
and that will make them
have indeed the same slope
of their four indifferent curves,
meaning the MRS might must be constant
and the same for any
combination of x1 and x2.
This concludes our discussion
of preferences and utility.
And we will then discuss how the ideas
of budget constraint,
as well as preferences
and utility combine in what
we call the consumer choice,
how the consumer uses their wallet
and their preferences or
their brain to find out
what is the best option they can afford,
what is the best thing,
what is the best affordable thing
that they can purchase and consume.
(upbeat music)